{"tossups": [{"question": "This woman\u2019s reign included oversight of a trading expedition to the Land of Punt and the building of the Unfinished Obelisk. Joyce Tyldesley [[TILDS-lee]] hypothesized that this woman\u2019s son and successor, Thutmose III [[TUT-mose \"the third\"]], contributed to the erasure of this woman\u2019s name from archaeological and written records. For the point, name this fifth ruler of the Eighteenth Dynasty of Egypt, the second confirmed female pharaoh.", "answer": "<b><u>Hatshepsut</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was commissioned to work on the Manhattan Project, where he helped Hans Bethe [[BEH-tuh]] develop a formula for calculating the yield of a fission bomb. With his colleagues, Julian Schwinger [[SHWING-uh]] and Shinichir\u014d Tomonaga [[shih-nee-CHIH-roh toh-moh-NAH-gah]], this man earned the 1956 Nobel Prize in Physics for his contributions to the field of quantum electrodynamics. For the point, name this American physicist, called the \"The Great Explainer,\" who proposed the parton model in particle physics.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Feynman</u></b> [[\"FINE\"-man]] (or Richard Phillips <b><u>Feynman</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "The song \"Amazing Grace\" was likely inspired by this figure's essay<em> A Faithful</em> <em>Narrative</em>. This man helped organize George Whitefield's [[\"WIT\"-\"fields\"]] ministerial tour of the Thirteen Colonies. This man, who led the Northampton Revivals, used the \"Fire and Brimstone\" style of preaching to convey the dangers of hell in a 1741 sermon. The \"Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God\" sermon was delivered by, for the point, which Puritan minister of the First Great Awakening?", "answer": "Jonathan <b><u>Edwards</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Near the waters of this river, the British incapacitated German-controlled drydocks during the St. Nazaire [[sehn nah-ZARE]] Raid to prevent the<em> Bismarck</em> from being repaired. During the War of the Vendee [[vahn-DEH]], Jean-Baptiste Carrier [[kahr-YEH]] mass-drowned monarchists from Nantes [[NONT]] in this river. The 17th-century Briare [[bree-AHR]] Canal connects this river to the Seine [[SEHN]]. The longest river in France is, for the point, what body of water which crosses into Orleans [[ohr-leh-AHN]] and Nevers [[neh-VEHR] as it flows to the Atlantic?", "answer": "<b><u>Loire</u></b> [[LWAHR]] River (accept <b><u>L\u00e9ger</u></b>; or <b><u>Liger</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This organization was given the island of Gotland under the promise that they would destroy the Victual Brothers. The disaster of the Battle on the Ice occurred to an autonomous branch of this group, the Livonian Order. Grand Duke Jogaila [[yoh-\"GUY\"-wah]] and Vytautas [[vee-TOH-tas]] the Great led a combined Polish-Lithuanian force to defeat this order at Grunwald [[GROON-vald]]. A Hochmeister [[HOK-my-stuh]] led, for the point, what German order of holy knights who led the Baltic Crusades?", "answer": "<b><u>Teutonic</u></b> [[too-TAH-nik]] Order (accept <b><u>Teutonic</u></b> Knights; or <b><u>Teutons</u></b>; accept <b><u>Deutscher Orden</u></b>; accept <b><u>Livonian</u></b> Order before mentioned; accept the full name: Order of <b><u>Brothers of the German House</u></b> of Saint Mary in Jerusalem)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man led a contingent of 1960s Republican congressmen, dubbed \"The Young Turks,\" who urged Gerald Ford to run in the 1968 presidential election. This man, who also served as Ford's Secretary of Defense, provided faulty evidence to President Bush that the Iraqi [[ih-RAK-kee]] government had weapons of mass destruction, prompting Operation Iraqi Freedom. For the point, name this Bush-era Secretary of Defense who died in June of 2021.", "answer": "Donald <b><u>Rumsfeld</u></b> (or Donald Henry <b><u>Rumsfeld</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During the Normandy invasion, this general brought his cocker spaniels \"Hitler\" and \"Rommel.\" This man challenged Patton to the \"Race to Messina\" [[meh-SEE-nuh]] during Operation Husky, losing by a mere few hours. This general prevented an Axis envelopment of his 8th Army at the Battle of Alam el Haifa [[ah-LAHM ell \"HIGH\"-fuh]] before scoring the first large-scale Allied victory of the war at El Alamein [[ell ah-lah-MEHN]]. For the point, name this British World War Two general.", "answer": "Bernard <b><u>Montgomery</u></b> (or Bernard Law <b><u>Montgomery</u></b>; prompt on \"Monty\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This dynasty experienced a brief restoration led by Zhang Xun [[ZHAHNG SHUN]] until he was forced to flee to the Legation Quarter. During this dynasty, an attempt to create a Christian theocratic dictatorship occurred during the Taiping [[\"TIE\"-\"PING\"]] Rebellion. The last ruler of this dynasty, the boy emperor Puyi [[POO-YEE]], was overthrown by Sun Yat-Sen in the Xinhai [[SHIN-\"HIGH\"]] Revolution. The Ming were overthrown by, for the point, what Chinese dynasty composed of Manchu royals?", "answer": "<b><u>Qing</u></b> [[CHING]] Dynasty (accept Great <b><u>Qing</u></b>; or D\u00e0 <b><u>Q</u><u>\u012b</u><u>ng</u></b>; accept <b><u>Manchu</u></b> Dynasty before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In punishment for participating in this war, Chief Metea [[meh-TEH-uh]] and his Potawatomi [[PAH-toh-WAH-toh-mee]] tribe were forced to move west of the Mississippi. Andrew Jackson appointed Winfield Scott to take field command from Henry Atkinson during this war, despite the latter's victory at the Battle of Bad Axe and the collapse of the British Band. The Sauk [[SAWK]] and Fox tribes fought for control of the Midwest with U.S. settlers in, for the point, what 1832 war?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Hawk</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In an effort to invalidate this proposal, a U.S. president recognized the Carranza government as legitimate. A political cartoon depicts a bomb named for this proposal exploding in the hands of Kaiser Wilhelm II. This proposal offered to recover states like California and Arizona, which were lost in the 1848 Treaty of Guadaloupe Hidalgo [[gwah-dah-LOOH-peh hee-DAHL-goh]]. The German Empire attempted to pull the state of Mexico into the Great War with, for the point, what \"Note\" named for a diplomat?", "answer": "<b><u>Zimmerman</u></b> Note (or <b><u>Zimmerman</u></b> Telegram)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The official report claims this pilot died after an Su-15 jet flew too close to his own MiG-15, forcing him to crash near the Chkalovsky [[chkah-LOF-skee]] Air Base. In reference to this man's accomplishment, Nikita Khrushchev [[KROOS-shoff]] stated [this man] \"didn't see anyone up there.\" This pilot shouted \"Off We Go!\" shortly before departing from Baikonur [[BY-koh-noor] Cosmodrome on Vostok I [[\"ONE\"]]. The first human in space was, for the point, which Soviet Cosmonaut?", "answer": "Yuri <b><u>Gagarin</u></b> [[gah-GAH-rin]] (or Yuri Alekseyevich <b><u>Gagarin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the dispersion of this group, two veterans and an eleven-week-old baby were killed by a police force led by Pelham D. Glassford. This group built a shanty town outside the Capitol called Anacostia Flats, where this group was attacked with gas by Douglas MacArthur\u2019s army. Led by Walter W. Waters, for the point, what group of Great War veterans marched on Washington, D.C. to demand payment during the worst of the Great Depression?", "answer": "<b><u>Bonus Army</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This god, sometimes worshipped as<em> Panoptes</em> [[pan-AHP-teez]], informs Demeter of the abduction of Persephone [[per-SEH-foh-nee]] by Hades. Julian the Apostate [[uh-PAH-\"state\"]] wrote a \"Hymn to [this deity],\" describing his conversion from Christianity to the worship of this god. This son of Hyperion, who was sometimes syncretized with Apollo, supposedly drove a golden chariot across the heavens. The Colossus of Rhodes depicted, for the point, what personification of the Sun from Greek mythology?", "answer": "<b><u>Helios</u></b> (or <b><u>Sol</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "During these wars' Battle of Bizani [[bih-ZAH-nee]], the first combat biplane was shot down while being flown by a volunteer Russian pilot. During these wars, Eleftherios Venizelos [[el-eff-THEHR-yohs veh-nee-ZEH-lohs]] pulled rank on King Constantine I to force a march on Thessalonica [[thess-uh-LOH-nee-kuh]]. The first of these wars concluded with the Treaty of London, resulting in Enver Pasha giving up most of the Ottoman territory in Europe. Bulgaria lost much of its territory in the second of, for the point, which wars named for a peninsula in southeastern Europe?", "answer": "<b><u>Balkan</u></b> Wars (accept First <b><u>Balkan</u></b> War or Second <b><u>Balkan</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This proposal asserted the need for free passage through the Dardanelles [[dar-dah-NELLS]] as well as the creation of an independent Poland. The last part of this proposal suggested the need for an international body to guarantee territorial integrity. This proposal led to the creation of the League of Nations, although the United States never joined. For the point, name this multi-part proposal by Woodrow Wilson arguing for national self-determination following World War One.", "answer": "The <b><u>Fourteen Point</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The introduction of the eunuch-magistrate is attributed to a queen of this empire named Semiramis [[seh-mih-RAHM-iss]]. An early use of the<em> casus belli</em> [[kah-SOOSS \"BELL\"-\"eye\"]], or \"justification of war,\" is found in the annals of this empire's Tiglath-Pileser I [[TIG-lath pie-LEE-ser \"the first\"]]. The subjugation of the Kingdom of Judah and the destruction of the rival city of Babylon is attributed to King Sennacherib [[seh-NAH-keh-rib] of this empire. For the point, name this Mesopotamian empire named for its capital city of Assur.", "answer": "<b><u>Assyria</u></b>n Empire (or Neo-<b><u>Assyria</u></b>n)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The first four of these events were named after the village of Stoke Mandeville in the UK, while a similar version of these events was held in \u00d6rnsk\u00f6ldsvik [\"urn\"-SHURLDS-veek] in 1976. A 2016<em> Nature</em> article detailed the advantages of running counterclockwise in these events. The 2000 edition of these events was plagued by a Spanish team's cheating during a Basketball ID tournament. For the point, name these games held after the Olympics that feature athletes with disabilities.", "answer": "<b><u>Paralympic</u></b>s (or <b><u>Paralympic</u></b> Games; accept Games of the <b><u>Paralympiad</u></b>; accept <b><u>International Wheelchair and Amputee Sports</u></b> World Games or <b><u>IWAS</u></b> World Games before \"\u00d6rnsk\u00f6ldsvik\"; prompt on \"Olympics\" before mentioned; accept descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Regarding this case, James Buchanan wrote to Associate Justice John Catron asking whether there would be a ruling before his inauguration. This case arose after John Emerson took the plaintiff to Fort Armstrong in Illinois and Fort Snelling in Wisconsin, both of which had outlawed slavery. For the point, name this Supreme Court case in which Roger Taney [[TAW-nee]] denied that U.S. citizenship could be afforded to people of African descent.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Dred Scott</u></b> v. John F. A. Sandford</em> (prompt on \u201cSandford\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Tennessee congressman Davy Crockett declared that his opposition to this act would\u201cnot make [him] ashamed in the Day of Judgment.\u201d This act led to John Eaton negotiating the Treaty of Dancing Rabbit Creek with the Choctaw nation. Resistance to this law led to many Cherokee being sent west on the \"Trail of Tears.\" The Southern Native Americans were deported west of the Mississippi by, for the point, what Andrew Jackson-era legislation?", "answer": "<b><u>Indian Removal</u></b> Act (prompt on \"Trail of Tears\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During a snowstorm power outage, a suburb of this city named Boucherville [[boo-shehr-VEEL]] intentionally derailed a diesel train and used it as an emergency generator. This city experienced the Murray-Hill riots after worker conditions became unsafe due to bombs being planted by the FLQ. A visit by Charles de Gaulle [[SHARL deh GAHL]] to this city in 1967 infamously led him to proclaim, \"Vive le Quebec Libre\" [[VEEV luh keh-BEK LEE-bruh]] while at this city's World Exposition. For the point, name this largest Francophone city in Canada.", "answer": "<b><u>Montr\u00e9al</u></b> [[mon-TREH-ahl]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Arab polymath al-Kindi [[KIN-dee]] introduced the use of this good as a general anesthetic, and Emperor Jahangir's [[jah-HAHN-\"gears\"]] consumption of wine and this drug made him an incapable ruler. Ending a war named for this good, the Treaty of Nanking created the five treaty ports and gave away the island of Hong Kong. China lost multiple 19th-century wars to the British named for, for the point, what narcotic, often found in \"poppy\" form, which is used to create heroin?", "answer": "<b><u>Opium</u></b> poppy (accept <b><u>Opium</u></b> War(s); prompt on \"Heroin\" before mentioned; do not accept \"Opiate\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Huolongjing</em> [[HWOH-LOHNG-JING]], or \"Fire Dragon Manual,\" is a book of instructions for creating this material's \"poison\" and \"divine\" varieties. While allegedly attempting to create the Elixir of Immortality, alchemists from a certain country invented this chemical compound, which is grouped with the compass, paper, and printing as the Four Great Inventions of China. For the point, name this explosive mixture used to propel projectiles.", "answer": "<b><u>Gunpowder</u></b> (accept <b><u>Black Powder</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A spontaneous example of these languages developed in Nicaragua in the 1980s in the midst of the Sandinista [[san-dih-NEE-stuh]] Revolution. The primate Nim Chimpsky [[\"CHIMP\"-skee]] supposedly learned one of these languages in a study done at Columbia University. Benedictine monk Pedro Ponce de Leon created one of these alphabets to help those who took vows of silence to communicate. For the point, name this type of language often developed for the hearing impaired.", "answer": "<b><u>Sign</u></b> Language (accept specific answers like American <b><u>Sign</u></b> Language; or <b><u>ASL</u></b>; prompt on answers indicating communicating with hand signals)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "A statue titled<em> Discovery of America</em> was removed from this building in 1958 due to it depicting Christopher Columbus towering over a cowering native woman. This building's namesake \"Rotunda\" houses the original<em> Surrender of General Cornwallis</em> by John Trumbull. Charles Bulfinch designed this government building's dome, on which the fresco<em> The</em> <em>Apotheosis of Washington</em> is painted. The Senate and House of Representatives chambers are in, for the point, what Washington, D.C. building?", "answer": "United States <b><u>Capitol</u></b> (accept The <b><u>Capitol</u></b>; or <b><u>Capitol</u></b> Building)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This U.S. state's town of Heppner lost a quarter of its population in a 1903 flood caused by a dam breach of Willow Creek. This state's largest city earned its nickname, \"Stumptown,\" due to its importance in the logging industry. John Jacob Astor established a namesake outpost which acted as a hub for his Pacific Fur Company in this state. For the point, name this terminus of a namesake pioneer trail, the home state of Astoria and Portland.", "answer": "<b><u>Oregon</u></b> (accept <b><u>Oregon</u></b> Trail)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Wealthy merchant Emon Saburo [[eh-MON sah-BOO-roh]] broke the bowl of a</u> <u>man in this profession named Kukai [[koo-KYE]], leading to the merchant's eight sons</u> <u>simultaneously falling ill and dying. Li Jong [[LEE JONG]] of the Chan [[CHAHN]] (+)</u> school held this occupation, though he was known for intentionally ignoring its rules by drinking alcohol to excess and eating meat. Often depicted (*)</b> meditating in Zen gardens, for the point, what clerical occupation is prominent in Buddhism?", "answer": "Buddhist <b><u>Monk</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bhikku</u></b>; or <b><u>Bhiksu</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Shower Posse, named for their \"showering\" of politicians with bribes, is a</u> <u>drug cartel aligned with this nation's conservative Labour Party. Enslaved Akans</u> <u>[[ak-KAHNS]] nearly wrested control of this island nation during (+)</u> Tacky's War. The Treaty of Madrid transferred this modern nation to England from Spain, after which this country was unofficially governed from Port (*)</b> Royal. The Maroon Wars occurred in, for the point, what Caribbean island nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Jamaica</u></b> (or <b><u>Jumieka</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A gift containing this animal's dung sent to Emperor L\u00ea Th\u00e1nh T\u00f4ng [[LEH</u> <u>TAHN TONG]] precipitated a failed invasion of Lan Xang [[LAHN SHAHNG]]. Over 500</u> <u>of these animals entered the stables of Seleucus [[seh-LOO-kus]] I after his daughter</u></b> <b>married</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Chandragupta</b> <b>Maurya</b> <b>[[CHAHN-drah-GOOP-tuh</b> <b>MAHR-yah]].</b> <b>The</b> <b>majority of these animals used to cross the Alps during the Second (*)</b> Punic [[PYOO-nik]] War were lost by Hannibal. For the point, name these large land mammals which saw heavy use in the kingdoms of Southeast Asia and India.", "answer": "<b><u>Elephant</u></b>s (accept Asian or Asiatic <b><u>Elephant</u></b>s; accept African <b><u>Elephant</u></b>s; accept White <b><u>Elephant</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This nation's presidency is named for the god of justice, Forseti. The Allies</u> <u>occupied this country when its sovereign was invaded in Operation Weser [[VEH-suh]]</u> <u>Exercise. This nation disputed fishing rights with the UK in the (+)</u> Cod Wars, and with the blessing of Christian X [[the tenth]], a plebiscite in this island nation decided to break away from (*)</b> Denmark. Sveinn Bj\u00f6rnsson [[SVAYN BYORN-son]] served as the first head of state of, for the point, what Nordic island nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Iceland</u></b> (or Lydveldid <b><u>\u00cdsland</u></b> [[EEZ-lahnd]])", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's chief lieutenant was a former African chieftain named Black Caesar,</u> <u>who previously ran a slave camp in the Upper Florida Keys. This man's ship, which</u> <u>was once a merchant vessel named the</u></b><em><b><u> Concord</u></b></em><b><u>, was renamed in reference to the last</u> <u>(+)</u> Stuart monarch. This man died off the coast of North Carolina in 1719 after having been (*)</b> run aground by the HMS<em> Bedford</em>. For the point, name this pirate, whose real name was Edward Teach, the captain of the<em> Queen Anne's Revenge</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Blackbeard</u></b> (accept Edward <b><u>Teach</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This state's Tangier [[tan-JEER]] Island, which sports an antiquated dialect of</u> <u>English, has physically shrunk by 67 percent over the past 170 years. The only city in</u> <u>this state to not be captured by the Union before the end of the U.S. Civil War was (+)</u> Lynchburg. Charlottesville is home to this state's flagship university as well as Monticello (*)</b> Estate, both designed by native-born Thomas Jefferson. For the point, name this state which contained the capital of the Confederate States of America.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Virginia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>An armored corps from this nation known as the \"Black Division\" was tasked</u> <u>with breaking the Nazi defense at the Falaise [[fah-LAYZ]] Gap. A team of</u> <u>mathematicians from this nation worked on breaking the German Enigma machine</u> <u>cipher led by Marian (+)</u> Rejewski. The majority of death camps, including Treblinka and (*)</b> Auschwitz, were located in this occupied nation. The September 1, 1939 Nazi invasion of, for the point, what nation ushered in the Second World War?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Poland</u></b> (or Rzeczpospolita <b><u>Polska</u></b>; accept Second <b><u>Polish</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>On the first day of this battle, John Buford spread his defenses around Herr</u> <u>Ridge, McPherson Ridge, and Seminary Ridge, anticipating the arrival of the (+)</u> Confederate army. This battle, which saw fierce fighting at Little Round Top, was lost for one side following the failed (*)</b> Pickett\u2019s Charge. For the point, name this U.S. Civil War battle fought over three days in 1863 in and around a namesake town in Pennsylvania.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Gettysburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}